<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <div>
      <head>Introduction</head>
      <p>This document provides the specific encoding principles for manuscripts and printed
         documents of the project e-ditiones.</p>
      <div>
         <head>The corpus</head>
         <p>The project e-ditiones aims to encode severals <date>17th century</date> French
            manuscripts and printed documents and, later, to present them on a digital library. We
            chose various literary genres, like drama, letters or novels.</p>
         <!-- Partie qui doit être discutée avec Simon -->
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>General principles</head>
         <p>Considering the fact that we have two major types of texts, as a reminder, printed
            documents and manuscripts, we made the decision to separate metadata from text. This
            way, we have the possibility to create two schemas, one specific to printed documents,
            the other to manuscripts. In order to rebuild a complete TEI file, we use
               <gi>xi:include</gi> which allows us to separate metadata from text and then have a
            complete final document.</p>
         <p>Another essential principle of the project is to use a minimal set of elements.</p>
         <!--  <figure>
             Simple test, il faut d'abord valider les schémas + rédiger les schémas en anglais 
            <graphic url=""/>
            attention au chemin de fichier en raison de l'usage de xi:include, il faut un chemin du type "/../filename"
            <head>Figure 1 - ODD-chaining</head>
            <figDesc>Representation of the use of ODD-chaining in the e-ditiones project </figDesc>
         </figure>-->
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>Document identifiers</head>
         <p>One of our priorities is to clearly identify the text once encoded. We chose to give to
            each document an unique identifier consisting of the first three letters of the project,
            an underscore and a four digit serial number. So, the identifier of the first text
            encoded will be <code>EDI_0001</code>.</p>
         <p>For each other subdivision, such as chapter, act, speech, paragraph or line, you just
            have to concatenat the idenfier of the upper subdivision with a dash and a new number.
            For example, if the text encoded is a play, the identifier <code>EDI_0001-1-3-4-5</code>
            can be understood as the fifth speech of the fourth scene, third act of the first play
            in the document with the identifier <code>EDI_0001</code>.</p>
         <p>If there is a front, such as a cast list, we decided to add a <code>O</code> between the
            identifier of the upper subdivision and the new number. For example
               <code>EDI_0001-0-1</code> indicates that this part is the first subdivision of the
            front from the document <code>EDI_0001</code>. In this way, we can immediately know the
            position of a subvision in the text.</p>
         <p>It might appear a little bit complicated but this method makes sure that every single
            line or paragraph can be clearly identify.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div>
      <head>The encoding</head>
      <div>
         <head>Headers encoding</head>
         <p>First, we chose to identify two differents types of headers : <list>
               <item>manuscripts</item>
               <item>printed documents</item>
            </list>
         </p>
         <div>
            <head>Manuscripts</head>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Printed documents</head>
         </div>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>Text encoding</head>
         <p>After the OCR of the text, its encoding will be completed in three phases : <list>
               <item>Level 1 : the encoding will distinguish form and content</item>
               <item>Level 2 : we will add semantic informations</item>
               <item>Level 3 : we will add linguistical informations</item>
            </list>
         </p>
         <p>Please note that at each level, all existing elements are still used and new elements
            are added to the existing ones.</p>
         <div>
            <head>First level</head>
            <p>The purpose of the first level is to distinguish between form and content. To do
               that, we chose to only use a few elements. First, at all levels our edition must
               contain a <gi>text</gi> element with the following namespace :
               @xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0". It checks the validation of the TEI schema.</p>
            <p>Then, at this level of encoding, all the text is included in the <gi>body</gi> and in
               a single <gi>p</gi>. Some informations are added at this point : concerning the
               content of the text, the element <gi>fw</gi> contains informations such as title,
               pagination or editor's notes. The other informations added are about the form of the
               text. We decided to employ the elements <gi>pb</gi> and <gi>lb</gi>. The first one,
                  <gi>pb</gi>, which marks the point where a new page begins, is useful in the way
               that it can be used to check the transcription but also to compare our edition with a
               reference edition. The second one, <gi>lb</gi>, which marks the point where a new
               line begins, provides graphical informations and can be used for an automatic
               encoding process. It has two required attributes : <att>break</att> and
                  <att>rend</att>. If a word is cut at the end of a line, <att>break</att> with the
               value "no" is useful in that the complete word can be establish again and be
               considere as a token. @rend shows which mark is used (a dash or an hyphen for
               example).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Second level</head>
            <p>At this level of encoding, we add manually some semantic informations. Considering
               that we want to use, as mentioned before, a minimal set of elements, we decided to
               only employ common elements. Despite this, in the case of texts such as plays or
               letters, the use of a few specific elements is recommended.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Common elements</head>
               <p>It is possible to use the following elements : <table>
                     <row role="label">
                        <cell>Element</cell>
                        <cell>Text type</cell>
                        <cell>Note</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell><gi>front</gi></cell>
                        <cell>any prefatory matter</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell><gi>div</gi></cell>
                        <cell>any text subdivision</cell>
                        <cell><att>type</att>,<att>n</att> and <att>xml:id</att> are required</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell><gi>back</gi></cell>
                        <cell>any type of appendix</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell><gi>head</gi></cell>
                        <cell>any type of heading</cell>
                        <cell>this can be used to clarify <gi>fw</gi></cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell><gi>list</gi>and<gi>item</gi></cell>
                        <cell>any type of list</cell>
                        <cell><att>n</att> and <att>xml:id</att> are required</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell><gi>orgName</gi>, <gi>persName</gi> and <gi>placeName</gi></cell>
                        <cell>any type of person, place or organisation</cell>
                        <cell>this can be useful for entity search</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell><gi>l</gi> and <gi>lg</gi></cell>
                        <cell>any type of line or line group</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell><gi>note</gi></cell>
                        <cell>any type of note</cell>
                        <cell>it can be used for a note by the autor, the editor or, rarely, added
                           during the encoding</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Specific elements</head>
               <p>There are only two exceptions, drama and letters.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>Drama</head>
                  <p>If the text encoded is a play, three new elements are allowed to be used :<table>
                        <row role="label">
                           <cell>Element</cell>
                           <cell>Text type</cell>
                           <cell>Note</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell><gi>sp</gi></cell>
                           <cell>contains a speech</cell>
                           <cell><att>n</att> and <att>xml:id</att> are required</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell><gi>stage</gi></cell>
                           <cell>any stage direction</cell>
                           <cell><emph>e.g.</emph> useful to study spoken words</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell><gi>speaker</gi></cell>
                           <cell>any speaker in a speech</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Letters</head>
                  <p>If the text encoded is a letter, two new elements are allowed to be used :<table>
                        <row role="label">
                           <cell>Element</cell>
                           <cell>Text type</cell>
                           <cell>Note</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell><gi>opener</gi></cell>
                           <cell>any text at the start of a letter</cell>
                           <cell><emph>e.g.</emph> a salutation or a dateline</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                           <cell><gi>closer</gi></cell>
                           <cell>any text at the end of a letter</cell>
                           <cell><emph>e.g.</emph> a salutation or a dateline</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table></p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Third level</head>
            <p>This level of encoding is automaticaly done. In order to add some linguistical
               informations, the original version of the text is normalized with the following
               elements : <gi>choice</gi>, <gi>orig</gi> and <gi>reg</gi>. Then, in order to process
               tokenization and lemmatization on the text, we decided to split it with <gi>seg</gi>
               and <gi>w</gi>. The first one, <gi>seg</gi> is used to represent any segmentation of
               the text. Note that sentences and clauses remain our basic units but we recommand to
               split a long sentence in several segments. The <gi>w</gi> is used to mark a single
               token. Regarding ponctuation, we decided to consider the marks as tokens; first,
               because more precision wouldn't be useful for our analyse and second, because with
               this choice, our encoding remains compatible with ELTeC.</p>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</body>
