<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<body xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <div>
      <head>Introduction</head>
      <p>This document provides the specific encodigng principles for manuscripts and printed
         documents of the project E-ditiones.</p>
      <div>
         <head>Document identifiers</head>
         <p>One of our priorities is to clearly identify the text once encoded. We chose to give to
            each document an unique identifier consisting of the first three letters of the project,
            an underscore and a four digit serial number. So, the identifier of the first text
            encoded will be <code>EDI_0001</code>.</p>
         <p>For each other subdivision, such as chapter, act, speech, paragraph or line, you just
            have to concatenat the idenfier of the upper subdivision with a dash and a new number.
            For example, if the text encoded is a play, the identifier <code>EDI_0001-1-3-4-5</code>
            can be understood as the fifth speech of the fourth scene, third act of the first play
            in the document with the identifier <code>EDI_0001</code>.</p>
         <p>If there is a front, such as a cast list, we decided to add a <code>O</code> between the
            identifier of the upper subdivision and the new number. For example
               <code>EDI_0001-0-1</code> indicates that this part is the first subdivision of the
            front from the document <code>EDI_0001</code>. In this way, we can immediately know the
            position in the text of one part or another.</p>
         <p>It might appear a little bit complicated but this method makes sure that every single
            line or paragraph can be clearly identify.</p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div>
      <head>The encoding</head>
      <div>
         <head>Headers encoding</head>
         <p>First, we choose to identify two differents types of headers : <list>
               <item>manuscripts</item>
               <item>printed documents.</item>
            </list>
         </p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>Text encoding</head>
         <p>After the OCR of the text, its encoding will be completed in three phases : <list>
               <item>First, the encoding will distinguish form and content</item>
               <item>Second, we will add semantic informations</item>
               <item>Third and last, we will add linguistical informations.</item>
            </list>
         </p>
         <div>
            <head>First level</head>
            <p>The first level purpose is to distinguish between form and content. To do that, we
               chose to only use a few elements. First, at all levels our edition must contain a
                  <gi>text</gi> element with the following namespace :
               @xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0". It checks the validation of the TEI schema.</p>
            <p>Then, at this level of encoding, all the text is included in the <gi>body</gi> and in
               a single <gi>p</gi>. Some informations are added at this point : concerning the
               content of the text, the element <gi>fw</gi> contains informations such as title,
               pagination or editor's notes. The other informations added are about the form of the
               text. We decided to employ the elements <gi>pb</gi> and <gi>lb</gi>. The first one,
                  <gi>pb</gi>, which marks the point where a new page begins, is useful in the way
               that it can be used to check the transcription but also to compare our edition with a
               reference edition. The second one, <gi>lb</gi>, which marks the point where a new
               line begins, provides graphical informations and can be used for an automatic
               encoding process. It has tow required attributes : @break and @rend. If a word is cut
               at the end of a line, @break="no" is useful in that the complete can be establish
               again and be considere as a token. @rend shows which mark is used (dash or an hyphen
               for example).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Second level</head>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Third level</head>
            <p/>
         </div>
      </div>
   </div>
</body>
